Chapter 70. The Sphinx.
It should not have been omitted that previous to completely stripping the
body of the Leviathan, he was beheaded.
Now, the beheading of the sperm whale is a scientific anatomical feat upon which
experienced whale surgeons very much pride themselves, and not without reason.
Consider that the whale has nothing that can properly be called a neck. On the
contrary, where his head and body seem to join, there in that very place is the
thickest part of him. Remember also that the surgeon must operate from above,
some 8 or 10 ft intervening between him and his subject, and that subject almost
hidden in a discolored, rolling, and oftentimes tumultuous and bursting sea.
Bear in mind, too, that under these untoward circumstances, he has to cut
many feet deep in the flesh, and in that subterraneanous matter, without so much
as getting one single peep into the ever contracting gash, thus made, he must
skillfully steer clear of all adjacent interdicted parts, and exactly divide
the spine at a critical point, hard by its insertion into the skull. Do you not
marvel then at Stub's boast that he demanded but 10 minutes to behead a sperm whale?
When first severed, the head is dropped a stern and held there by a cable till
the body is stripped. That done, if it belonged to a small whale, it is hoisted
on deck to be deliberately disposed of.
But with a full-grown Leviathan, this is impossible. For the sperm whale's head
embraces nearly onethird of his entire bulk, and completely to suspend such a
burden as that, even by the immense tackles of a whaler, this were as vain a
thing as to attempt weighing a Dutch barn in jeweler scales.
The Peekquad's whale being decapitated and the body stripped, the head was
hoisted against the ship's side, about halfway out of the sea, so that it might
yet in great part be boyed up by its native element. And there, with the
strained craft steeply leaning over to it, by reason of the enormous downward
drag from the lower mast head, and every yard arm on that side projecting like a
crane over the waves, there that blood dripping head hung to the Peekquad's
waist, like the giant hole of the girdle of Judith.
When this last task was accomplished, it was noon, and the seammen went below to
their dinner. Silence rained over the before tumultuous but now deserted deck.
An intense copper calm, like a universal yellow lotus, was more and more
unfolding its noless, measurless leaves upon the sea.
A short space elapsed, and up into this nolessness came Ahab alone from his
cabin. Taking a few turns on the quarter deck, he paused to gaze over the side.
Then slowly getting into the main chains, he took Stub's long spade, still
remaining there after the whale's decapitation, and striking it into the lower part of
the half suspended mass, placed its other end crutchwise under one arm, and
so stood leaning over with eyes attentively fixed on this head.
It was a black and hooded head, and hanging there in the midst of so intense
a calm, it seemed the sphinxes in the desert. "Speak thou vast and venerable
head," muttered Ahab, which though ungarnished with a beard, yet here and
there looks horry with mosses. "Speak, mighty head, and tell us the secret
thing that is in thee. Of all divers, thou hast dived the deepest. That head
upon which the upper sun now gleams, has moved amid this world's foundations.
where unrecorded names and navies rust and untold hopes and anchors rot. Where
in her murderous hold this frigot earth is ballasted with bones of millions of
the drowned, there in that awful waterland, there was thy most familiar home.
Thou has been where bell or diver never went. Hast slept by many a sailor's side
where sleepless mothers would give their lives to lay them down. Thou sawest the
locked lovers when leaping from their flaming ship. Heart to heart they sank
beneath the exalting wave. True to each other when heaven seemed false to them.
Thou sawest the murdered mate when tossed by pirates from the midnight
deck. For hours he fell into the deeper midnight of the insatiate Maw, and his
murderers still sailed on unharmed, while swift lightnings shivered the
neighboring ship that would have borne a righteous husband to outstretched longing arms.
Oh head, thou has seen enough to split the planets and make an infidel of Abraham,
and not one syllable is thine.
Sail ho! Cried a triumphant voice from the main mast head. "I now that's
cheering," cried Ahab, suddenly erecting himself, while whole thunderclouds swept
aside from his brow. "That lively cry upon this deadly calm might almost
convert a better man. Wear away!" Three points on the starboard bow, sir, and
bringing down her breeze to us. Better and better man. Would now St. Paul would
come along that way into my breezelessness bringing his breeze. Oh
nature and oh soul of man, how far beyond all utterances are your linked analogies.
Not the smallest atom stirs or lives on matter, but has its cunning duplicate in mind.